Guide to the William Dwight Whitney papers relating to the Atharvaveda
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William Dwight Whitney papers relating to the Atharvaveda
1850-1894
GEN MSS 1125
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.09
(6 boxes)
Autograph manuscripts relating to Whitney's research and translations of the Atharvaveda, including a copy in Sanskrit, with notes about source manuscripts; a transliteration, collated with manuscripts in Berlin, Paris, Oxford, London, and Tübingen; a draft for his Index Verborum; and unidentified drafts and notes, most apparently relating to his English translation. Drafts and notes include material by Rudolf von Roth and annotations by Charles Rockwell Lanman.
Whitney, William Dwight, 1827-1894
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the family of William Dwight Whitney, 1924.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
William Dwight Whitney (1827-1894)
William Dwight Whitney (1827-1894), linguist and Yale University professor of Sanskrit and comparative philology, 1854-1894. Whitney's publications on the Atharvaveda, a sacred text of Hinduism, include a German translation with Rudolf von Roth (Berlin: F. Dümmler, 1855-1856); an Index Verborum (New Haven: American Oriental Society, 1881); and a posthumously-published English translation, completed by Charles Rockwell Lanman, Harvard Oriental Series, volumes 7-8 (Cambridge: Harvard University, 1905).
Scope and Contents
Autograph manuscripts relating to Whitney's research and translations of the Atharvaveda, including a copy in Sanskrit, with notes about source manuscripts; a transliteration, collated with manuscripts in Berlin, Paris, Oxford, London, Tübingen; a draft for his Index Verborum; and unidentified drafts and notes, most apparently relating to his English translation. Drafts and notes include material by Rudolf von Roth and annotations by Charles Rockwell Lanman.
Vedas. Atharvaveda; Vedas. Atharvaveda. English; Hindu literature, Sanskrit -- Translations into English; Hindu literature, Sanskrit -- Translations into German; Indic philology; Philologists -- United States; Sanskrit literature -- Translations into English; Sanskrit literature -- Translations into German; Philologists -- United States -- 19th century; Lanman, Charles Rockwell, 1850-1941; Roth, Rudolf von, 1821-1895; Whitney, William Dwight, 1827-1894
- Copy in Sanskrit, with notes about source manuscripts, undated; (1 bound volume) (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Copy in Sanskrit (notes formerly laid in volume), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Transliteration, collated with manuscripts in Berlin, Paris, Oxford, London, and Tübingen, 1851 October-1852 March; (2 bound volumes) (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
- Transliteration (notes formerly laid in volume 1), undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Transliteration (notes formerly laid in volume 2), undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- "Index Verborum Vedicorum", 1873-1881; (1 bound volume) (Box 3, Folder 7)
- "Index Verborum Vedicorum" (notes formerly laid in), undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Unidentified notes and drafts, circa 1850-circa 1894 (Box 4, Folder 9-16)
- Unidentified notes and drafts, circa 1850-circa 1894 (Box 5, Folder 17-18)
- Unidentified notes and drafts, circa 1850-circa 1894 (Box 6, Folder 19-25)